<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="dactyl://content/help.xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "dactyl://content/dtd">

<document
    name="faq"
    title="&dactyl.appName; FAQ"
    xmlns="&xmlns.dactyl;"
    xmlns:html="&xmlns.html;">

            <h1 style="margin-top: 0;">Frequently Asked Questions</h1>
            <p>
                Below is a list of some of the commonest questions that come to
                our attention, along with their hopefully satisfactory answers.
                Please take a minute to search for your answers here before
                asking the <link topic="&dactyl.list.href;">mailing list</link> or
                <link topic="&dactyl.irc;">irc channel</link>,
                and don't forget to peruse the
                <link topic="&dactyl.hg.latest;&dactyl.name;/NEWS">NEWS file</link> for recent
                changes that might throw you off balance.
            </p>

            <toc start="2"/>

            <h2 tag="faq-general">General</h2>
            <h3 tag="faq-fork">Why did Pentadactyl split from Vimperator?</h3>
            <p>
                The reasons for the fork were mostly political, but mostly
                boil down to the fact that the current maintainer, while
                making no substantial contributions to the project for several
                years, continues to exercise full editorial control while
                actively soliciting donations with no transparency whatever.
                We considered the latter especially a slight on both our
                developers and our users, and after a considerable escalation
                of the degree of offense felt compelled to leave the project.
            </p>
            <p>
                However, though we could no longer justify supporting the
                Vimperator project, we've invested considerable time and
                energy into the code over these past several years and still
                use and care about it. For that reason, we've decided to
                publicly release our personal changes and continue to develop
                the extension under a different name.
            </p>

            <h3 tag="faq-differences">What differentiates Pentadactyl from Vimperator?</h3>
            <p>
                The main difference is that Vimperator's most active
                developers have moved on to Pentadactyl. More qualitative
                changes may be found in the
                <link topic="&dactyl.hg.latest;&dactyl.name;/NEWS">change log</link>,
                but essentially add up to what we consider more active and
                thoughtful development. Among the most visible differences, as
                of Pentadactyl 1.0, are more extensive Firefox 4 support,
                significantly better startup time and completion performance,
                considerably better :sanitize and private mode support, a
                greatly improved incremental find implementation, major
                improvements in Ex command parsing (including the ability to
                separate commands with | and split long commands across lines),
                conditionals (<ex>:if</ex>/<ex>:else</ex>) in configuration
                files, greatly updated documentation, and a number of bug fixes.
            </p>

            <h3 tag="faq-statussymbols">What do the "[-+♥]" symbols in the status bar mean?</h3>
            <p>
                These indicate that you can move backward through history,
                that you can move forward through history, and that the page is
                bookmarked, respectively. See also <ex>:help</ex>
                <t>status-line</t>.
            </p>

            <h3 tag="faq-lasttab">How can I prevent <k>d</k> on the last tab from closing the window?</h3>
            <p><ex>:set!</ex> <hl key="HelpOpt">browser.tabs.closeWindowWithLastTab</hl>=<hl key="Boolean">false</hl></p>

            <h3 tag="faq-autocomplete"><strut/>How can I prevent the command line completion list showing until I press <k name="Tab" link="c_&lt;Tab>"/>?</h3>
            <p>
                You can disable it entirely with <se opt="autocomplete"/> or for
                specific types of command completion by choosing more
                restrictive values. See <ex>:help</ex> <o>autocomplete</o> and
                <o>wildmode</o>.
            </p>

            <h3 tag="faq-editor-fork">Why doesn't external input field editing work with my <o>editor</o> setting?</h3>
            <p>
                Unfortunately, external editors which return immediately, before
                editing is complete, are not supported. This means that
                <tt>gvim</tt>, for instance, must be run with the <em>-f</em>
                flag, and editors run from a terminal must not connect to a
                remote process. In the case of Rxvt-unicode, this means that the
                <tt>urxvtc</tt> program is not an option, and Gnome Terminal is
                very likely not useable under any circumstances.
            </p>
            <note>
                If you are using a version of Firefox newer than 4.0 beta 7 and
                a version of Pentadactyl less than 1.0 βeta 4, you'll need to
                upgrade the latter.
            </note>

            <h3 tag="faq-symlinks">Why can't I build/install from the Mercurial repository on Windows®?</h3>
            <p>
                We use symbolic links in our repository to deal with certain
                files which are common across projects. Mercurial for Windows®,
                unfortunately, doesn't deal with these very well. However,
                adding the following lines to the <tt>.hg\hgrc</tt> file in your
                repository should make things work:
            </p>
            <code><hl key="Key">[hooks]</hl>
update = <str delim="">python:common/contrib/fix_symlinks.py:fix_symlinks</str>
preupdate = <str delim="">python:common/contrib/fix_symlinks.py:fix_symlinks</str>
commit = <str delim="">python:common/contrib/fix_symlinks.py:fix_symlinks</str>
precommit = <str delim="">python:common/contrib/fix_symlinks.py:fix_symlinks</str></code>

            <h2 tag="faq-open"><ex>:open</ex> behavior</h2>
            <h3 tag="faq-urlsep">Why can't I separate URLs in <ex>:open</ex> with a comma anymore?</h3>
            <p>See <ex>:help <o>urlseparator</o></ex></p>

            <h3 tag="faq-hidden-engines">
                <strut/>
                <ex>:open <a>search-string</a></ex> or <ex>:open <str delim="">google</str> <a>search-string</a></ex>
                results in <str>The url is not valid and cannot be loaded</str>
            </h3>
            <p>
                You need a valid search engine name in the <o>defsearch</o>
                option. If it's stopped working suddenly, there's a good chance
                that you've either deleted a search engine or changed its alias.
                You can check by invoking

                <code><ex>:dialog <str delim="">searchengines</str></ex></code>

                There also appears to be a Firefox bug whereby the default
                engines are hidden after an update. This can be remedied by
                invoking

                <code style="position: relative"><ex>:js</ex> services.browserSearch.getEngines().forEach(<em>function</em> (e) e.hidden = <hl key="Boolean">false</hl>)</code>
            </p>

            <h2 tag="faq-keys">Key bindings</h2>
            <h3 tag="faq-website-keys">How can I use the native key bindings of sites like Gmail?</h3>
            <p>
                See the <o>passkeys</o> option to automatically pass specific
                keys on sites of your choosing, or <t>autocmd-examples</t> to
                automatically enter <em>Pass Through</em> mode for certain websites.
            </p>

            <h3 tag="faq-passkeys-autocmd">Why doesn't my modes.passAllKeys autocmd work anymore?</h3>
            <p>See <t>faq-website-keys</t> above.</p>

            <h2 tag="faq-hints">Hints</h2>
            <h3 tag="faq-hintkeys">How can I use keys other than numbers for hinting?</h3>
            <p>Use the <o>hintkeys</o> option.</p>

            <h3 tag="faq-hintkeys-uppercase"><strut/>How can I display my hints in upper case but type them in lower case?</h3>
            <p>
                If you use alphabetic characters for your <o>hintkeys</o> and
                would like to be able to type them in lower case but still have
                the hints displayed in upper case, use:
            </p>
            <code><ex>:highlight</ex> <em>-a</em> Hint <hl key="Key">text-transform</hl>: <str delim="">uppercase</str>;</code>

            <h3 tag="faq-hint-hidetext">How can I hide the hint text for input and image hints?</h3>
            <p>
                If you'd only like to show the numbered portion of hints, you
                can do so with:
            </p>
            <code><ex>:highlight</ex> Hint<str delim="">::after</str> <hl key="Key">content</hl>: attr(<str delim="">number</str>) <hl key="Key">!important</hl>;</code>

</document>

<!-- vim:se sts=4 sw=4 et: -->
