<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="dactyl://content/help.xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "dactyl://content/dtd">

<document
    name="hints"
    title="&dactyl.appName; Hints"
    xmlns="&xmlns.dactyl;"
    xmlns:html="&xmlns.html;">

<h1 tag="hints">Hints</h1>
<toc start="2"/>

<p>
    Hints are an easy way to interact with web pages without using
    your mouse. In Hints mode, &dactyl.appName; highlights and
    numbers all clickable elements. The elements can be selected
    either by typing their numbers, or typing parts of their text to
    narrow them down. While the default action is to click the
    selected link, other actions are available, including saving the
    resulting link, copying its URL, or saving an image. For each
    of these actions, only the set of applicable elements is
    highlighted.
</p>

<item>
    <tags>quick-hints hint-mode</tags>
    <tags>f</tags>
    <strut/>
    <spec>f<a>hint</a></spec>
    <description>
        <p>
            Start <t>hint-mode</t>. In this mode, every clickable
            element (as defined by the <o>hinttags</o> option) is
            highlighted and numbered.  Elements can be selected
            either by typing their number, or by typing part of
            their text to narrow down the result. When an element
            has been selected, it is automatically clicked and hint
            mode ends. Additionally, the following keys have
            special meanings in Hints mode:
        </p>
        <dl>
            <dt><k name="CR"/></dt>
            <dd>Selects the first highlighted element, or that
                focused by <k name="Tab"/>.</dd>

            <dt><k name="Tab"/></dt>
            <dd>Moves the focus to the next hintable element</dd>

            <dt><k>\</k></dt>
            <dd>Temporarily treats all numbers (or other keys, depending on the
                value of <o>hintkeys</o>) as ordinary text</dd>

            <dt><k name="Esc"/></dt>
            <dd>Exits Hints mode without selecting an element</dd>
        </dl>
    </description>
</item>

<item>
    <tags>F</tags>
    <strut/>
    <spec>F<a>hint</a></spec>
    <description>
        <p>
            Start <t>hint-mode</t>, but the selected elements
            are clicked with the <k name="Shift" link="false"/> key pressed,
            which has the normal effect of opening it in a new tab
            (depending on the value of the
            <pref>browser.tabs.loadInBackground</pref> preference).
        </p>
    </description>
</item>

<item>
    <tags>extended-hints</tags>
    <tags>;</tags>
    <strut/>
    <spec>;<a>mode</a><a>hint</a></spec>
    <description>
        <p>
            Start an extended hints mode. Extended hints are exactly like
            <t>quick-hints</t>, except that each sub-mode highlights a
            more specialized set of elements, and performs a unique action on
            the selected link. Because of the panoply of extended hint modes
            available, after pressing <k>;</k>, pressing <k name="Tab" link="false"/>
            brings up the completion list with each hints mode and its description.
        </p>

        <p><a>mode</a> may be one of:</p>

        <ul>
            <li tag=";;"><em>;</em> to focus a link</li>
            <li tag=";?"><em>?</em> to show information about the element (incomplete)</li>
            <li tag=";s"><em>s</em> to save its destination</li>
            <li tag=";f"><em>f</em> to focus a frame</li>
            <li tag=";F"><em>F</em> to focus a frame or pseudo-frame</li>
            <li tag=";o"><em>o</em> to open its location in the current tab</li>
            <li tag=";t"><em>t</em> to open its location in a new tab</li>
            <li tag=";b"><em>b</em> to open its location in a new background tab</li>
            <li tag=";w"><em>w</em> to open its destination in a new window</li>
            <li tag=";O"><em>O</em> to generate an <ex>:open</ex> prompt with hint’s URL</li>
            <li tag=";T"><em>T</em> to generate a <ex>:tabopen</ex> prompt with hint’s URL (like <k>;O</k>)</li>
            <li tag=";W"><em>W</em> to generate a <ex>:winopen</ex> prompt with hint’s URL (like <k>;T</k>)</li>
            <li tag=";a"><em>a</em> to add a bookmark</li>
            <li tag=";S"><em>S</em> to add a search keyword for the hint’s form</li>
            <li tag=";v"><em>v</em> to view its destination source</li>
            <li tag=";V"><em>V</em> to view its destination source in the external editor</li>
            <li tag=";y"><em>y</em> to yank its destination location</li>
            <li tag=";Y"><em>Y</em> to yank its text description</li>
            <li tag=";A"><em>A</em> to yank its anchor URL</li>
            <li tag=";c"><em>c</em> to open its context menu</li>
            <li tag=";i"><em>i</em> to open an image</li>
            <li tag=";I"><em>I</em> to open an image in a new tab.</li>
        </ul>

        <p>
            Of the previous modes, the value of the <o>hinttags</o>
            option is used to choose the highlighted elements,
            unless an override can be found in
            <o>extendedhinttags</o>.
        </p>
    </description>
</item>

<item>
    <tags>g;</tags>
    <strut/>
    <spec>g;<a>mode</a><a>hint</a></spec>
    <description>
        <p>
            Start an extended hints mode and stay there until
            <k name="Esc"/> is pressed. Like <k>;</k>, except that
            after a hint is selected, hints remain visible so that
            another one can be selected with the same action as the
            first.
        </p>
    </description>
</item>

</document>

<!-- vim:se sts=4 sw=4 et: -->
